<?xml-model href="../../ODD/out/Utopia.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chapter 1. Descripción de la isla</title>
            <funder>This work has been developed thanks to a doctoral fellowship granted in 2020
               by the Spanish Ministry of Universities</funder>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Inmaculada Ureña Asensio</name>
               <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEIPublisher</publisher>
            <pubPlace><ref>http://utopiadethomasmoro-digitaledition.com/</ref></pubPlace>
            <date>2024</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Utopia de Thomas Moro, traducida de latin en Caſtellano por Don Geronimo
                  Antonio de Medinilla i Porres, Cauallero de la Orden de Santiago,
                  Cavallerizo de ſu Mageſtad, Señor de las Villas de Bocos, Rozas, i Remolino,
                  Corregidor, i Iuſticia mayor de la Ciudad de Cordova, i ſu tierra. </title>
               <author role="writer" xml:id="person-1">Thomas More (1478-1535)</author>
               <author role="translator" xml:id="person-2">Gerónimo de Medinilla y Porres
                  (1590-c.1642)</author>
               <publisher>por Salvador de Cea Tesa</publisher>
               <date>1637</date>
               <pubPlace>Córdoba</pubPlace>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>The Utopia of Thomas More, in Latin from the edition of March 1518, and
                  in English from the first edition of Ralph Robinson's translation in
                  1551</title>
               <title/>
               <author role="writer" ref="#person-1">Thomas More (1478-1535)</author>
               <author role="translator" xml:id="person-3">Ralph Robinson (1520-1577)</author>
               <editor>L. H. Lupton</editor>
               <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
               <date>1895</date>
               <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This edition was developed as part of my thesis dissertation titled "A Digital
               Edition of the 1637 Spanish translation of Thomas More's Utopia". The processes
               of data modeling, encoding and publishing the edition was done during a research
               visit to the Digital Scholarship Group and the Women Writers Project at Northeastern University (Boston, USA).</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>The aim of this edition is to offer a side-by-side edition of the first printed translation of Thomas More's <hi>Utopia</hi>
               into Spanish plus three accompanying texts: a modernization of Gerónimo de Medinilla's 1637 rendering, the Latin text taken from
               the 1518 March edition and the 1551 English translation by Ralph Robinson.</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>For the modernization of the Spanish translation, graphs, punctuation and accentuation have been adapted to 
                  today's orthographical norms as established by the Real Academia de la Lengua Española in its <hi>Diccionario</hi> (2023)
                  and <hi>Ortografía de la Lengua Española</hi> (2010).</p>
            </normalization>                
            <segmentation>
               <p>The texts have been segmented into sentences to facilitate alignment. In the framework of the present edition,
                  a sentence is defined as the text between two periods, disregarding other linguistic conventions.</p>
            </segmentation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>Identifiers are made up by concatenating the language reference code,
               chapter number, segment number and segment order in the sentence.
               Sentences are connected by <att>corresp</att>. A previous <att>type</att>
               indicates whether the segment has been translated or not by Medinilla. Thus, if
               a segment is untranslated, it will not carry the <att>corresp</att>.
               The <att>n</att> of segment is also key in the alignment process</p>
         </refsDecl>           
         <schemaSpec ident="TEI"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="es">seventeenth-century Spanish</language>
            <language ident="es-ES">Castilian Spanish</language>
            <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            <language ident="en">sixteenth-century English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-10-31">Version 1.0</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="base" xml:lang="es">
            <pb n="1r"/>
            <head type="work">RELACION, QVE HIZO Rafael Hithlodeo, excelẽte varõ, del felice
               eſtado de la republica de VTOPIA, ordenada por Thomas Moro, Vizcõde, Ciudadano de la
               inſigne Ciudad de Londres en Inglaterra. </head>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head type="chapter">DESCRIPCION DE LA ISLA. Cap. I.</head>
               <ab>
                  <seg n="1.1" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-01-1" n="es 1.1">La Isla de los Vtopienſes, en el medio ſe
                        eſtiẽnde a docientos mil paſſos, i por larguiſsimo eſpacio no ſe eſtrecha
                        conſiderablemente; mas alfin de entrambos aidos cabos ſe va enſangoſtando: i
                        eſtas puntas en circunferẽcia de cinquenta mil paſſos, dexan la Isla en
                        forma de Luna nueva.<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-1-1"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.2" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-02-1" n="es 1.2">Eſtas extremidades <pb n="1v"/>convatidas del mar ſe
                        hallan diſtantes la una dela otra otros onze mil; i el mar defendido de los
                        vientos.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.3" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-03-1" n="es 1.3">Entre eſtos braços forma un apacible lago,
                        dexando un puerto acomodado, deſde donde por ſu oportunidad embian ſus
                        flotas a otras Provincias, i Paiſes.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.4" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-04-1" n="es 1.4">Las gargantas de las entradas de la una parte
                        con los bancos, i bados; i de la otra con diſsimulados eſcollos ponen
                        eſpanto al que pretẽde entrar, como enemigo.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.5" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-05-1" n="es 1.5">Casi en el medio deſte eſpacio ſe vee otra
                        roca, notan peligroſa: en cuya eminencia han fabricado un fuerte, donde
                        tienen preſidio.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-1-2"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.6" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-06-1" n="es 1.6">Hallanſe otros muchos eſcollos ocultos, i por
                        eſto dañoſos: ellos ſolamente tienen conocimiento de aquellos canales: de
                        donde procede que raras vezes el eſtrangero, que no ſea aviſado de alguno de
                        la Vtopia, pueda penetrallos, i quando con afan entre ſin rieſgo, no
                        governandoſe por ciertasguias pueſtas en la ribera, vendra qualquiera grãde
                        enemiga armada a dar al trabes.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.7" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-07-1" n="es 1.7">De la otra parte ai un puerto baſtantemẽte
                        frequentado; i el deſembarcadero fortificado por arte, i naturaleza: de
                        manera, que poca gente de guerra pondrã en retirada i rebatiran el impetu de
                        copioſo exercito.<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-1-3"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.8" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-08-1" n="es 1.8">Ai opinion (i la apariencia del lugar lo
                        mueſtra) que aquella tierra en lo antiguo eſtava rodeada del mar.<anchor
                           n="4" xml:id="note-1-4"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.9" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-09-1" n="es 1.9">Mas Vtopo, de quien tomò nombre la Isla, por
                        averla conquiſtado (porque primero ſe llamava Abraxa) reduxo aquella 
                        muche<pb n="2r"/>dumbre ruſtica, i groſſera a eſta manera de vivir humana, i civil, qual
                        ſigue todo el linaje de los hõbres.<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-1-5"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.10" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-10-1" n="es 1.10">Cortò un Iſthmo de diez mil paſſos, porel
                        qual eſtava Vtopia continente con la tierra firme, con que quedò hecha
                           Isla.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-1-6"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.11" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-11-1" n="es 1.11">Aviendo conſtriñido, no ſolo a los moradores
                        antiguos, mas tambien a ſus ſoldados, por no cauſar afrenta a aquellos: i
                        con tanto numero de operarios en breviſſimo tiempo acabò el trabajo, dexando
                        admirados los pueblos vezinos, que al principio burlavan del intento.<anchor
                           n="7" xml:id="note-1-7"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.12" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-12-1" n="es 1.12">Ai en eſta Isla cinquenta i quatro Ciudades,
                        conformes en lengua, inſtitutos,i leyes, i caſi a un modelo fabricadas, en
                        quanto el ſitio lo permite.<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-1-8"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.13" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-13-1" n="es 1.13">Las mas cercanas eſtan deſviadas veinte i
                        quatro mil paſſos; mas ninguna ſe halla tã apartada una de otra, que en un
                        dia no pueda hazer jornada a ellas un peon.<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-1-9"
                        /></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.14" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-14-1" n="es 1.14">Tres Ciudadanos expertos, i ancianos de cada
                        una deſtas Ciudades <app>
                           <lem>todos los años concurren</lem>
                           <rdg wit="1790">concurren todos los años</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="1805">concurren todos los años</rdg>
                        </app> en Amauroto, la qual por eſtar aſſentada en medio de la Isla, es a
                        todos cōmoda, i tenida por principal, i Cabeça, donde tratan de la cauſa
                        comun i publica de toda la Vtopia.<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-1-10"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.15" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-15-1" n="es 1.15">Las Ciudades no tienen de termino paſſados de
                        veinte mil paſſos en contorno, algunas mas, conforme eſtan deſviadas, i
                        apartadas mas, o menos entre ſi, ninguna dellas deſſea eſtender, o dilatar
                        ſu diſtrito, juzgandoſe antes vſufrutuarios labradores de los campos, que
                        ſeñores dellos.<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-1-11"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.16" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-16-1" n="es 1.16">Tienen alquerias mui prevenidas <pb n="2v"/>de todos los
                        inſtrumentos para la labor, i agricultura; i a eſtos cortijos van a poblar
                        los Ciudadanos.<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-1-12"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.17" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-17-1" n="es 1.17">Ninguna familia ruſtica deſtas tiene menos de
                        quarenta perſonas, excepto dos hombres del campo.<anchor n="13"
                           xml:id="note-1-13"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.18" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-18-1" n="es 1.18">A todo eſle numero ſe le feñala padre, i
                        madre de familias, por edad, i coftumbres venerables; i a cada treinta
                        Cortijos ſe le propone Cabeça.<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-1-14"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.19" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-19-1" n="es 1.19">Buelven a la Ciudad en cada un año veinte de
                        los deſtas familias, de los que han reſidido dos en las alquerias.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.20" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-20-1" n="es 1.20">Suceden a eſtos otros tantos de la Ciudad,
                        para que ſean exercitados en la agricultura, por los que quedan expertos,
                        con la reſidencia de vn año, i que el venidero enſeñen a otros, <app>
                           <lem>a intento</lem>
                           <rdg wit="1790">con el fin de</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="1805">con el fin de</rdg>
                        </app> que no falte en todos la experiẽcia de la labranca; para que al
                        tiempo de recogerlos frutos ſe hallen abiles.<anchor n="15"
                           xml:id="note-1-15"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.21" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-21-1" n="es 1.21">I aunque eſta manerade renovar la agricultura
                        ſe acoſtumbra; porqueninguno ſe halle obligado a continuar la vida ruſtica
                        mas tiempo, no por eſto muchos que ſe deleitaſſen en la agricultura dejaſſen
                        de eſtar alli mas años.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.22" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-22-1" n="es 1.22">Los labradores cultivan el terreno, ſuſtentan
                        los animales, aperciben leña, i la conducen a la Ciudad por tierra, o por
                        mar, como les viene mas a propoſito.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.23" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-23-1" n="es 1.23">Sacan con admirable artificio una infinidad
                        de pollos; porque ſin empollarlas gallinas, con un calor proporcionado los
                        dan vida, i deſpues los hombres los abrigan, i goviernan.<anchor n="16"
                           xml:id="note-1-16"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.24" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-24-1" n="es 1.24">Suſtentan pocos Cavallos, i ferozes, de los
                        quales ſe ſirben ſolamente en las empreſas de <pb n="3r"/>guerra: porque las demas
                        labores de cultivar, i conduzir, las executan con los bueyes, los quales
                        bien que ſean mas lentos, que los cauallos, toda via en el exercicio ſon mas
                        ſufridos, i menos ſujetos a enfermedades, fuera de que ſon de menos gaſto: i
                        quando no ſe puede por la vejez uſar dellos ſe pueden comer.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.25" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-25-1" n="es 1.25">Siembran ſolamente trigo, beben vino de ubas,
                        i gaſtan ſidra, o agua pura, o cocida con regaliz, de que tienen mucha
                        abundancia.</s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.26" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-26-1" n="es 1.26">I aunque tantean quanta vitualla ſe conſuma
                        en la Ciudad, i el contorno, ſin embargo ſiembran mas para dar a los
                           vezinos.<anchor n="17" xml:id="note-1-17"/></s>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.27" type="sentence">
                     <s xml:id="es-1-27-1" n="es 1.27">Todo inſtrumento de la labrança, ſe toma de
                        la Ciudad, por mano del Magiſtrado, ſincoſta alguna: i muchos concurren
                        todos los meſes en los pueblos a las fieſtas ſolemnes: quando es tiempo de
                        ſegar los panes, los que gobiernan la labrança aviſan a los Magiſtrados,
                        quanto numero de Ciudadanos deban embiar a la ſiega; i concurriendo todos
                        aun tiempo en dia ſereno, caſi ponen en cobro todo el grano.<anchor n="18"
                           xml:id="note-1-18"/></s>
                  </seg>
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="modernization" xml:lang="es">
            <pb n="1r"/>
            <head type="work"> Relación que hizo Rafael Hithlodeo, excelente varón, del feliz
               estado de la república de Utopia, ordenada por Thomas Moro, vizconde, ciudadano de la
               insigne ciudad de Londres en Inglaterra.</head>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head type="chapter">Descripción de la isla. Capítulo 1.</head>
               <ab>
                  <seg n="1.1" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-01-1" n="em 1.1" corresp="#es-1-01-1">La Isla de los
                        Utopienses en el medio se extiende a doscientos mil pasos, y por larguísimo
                        espacio no se estrecha considerablemente; mas al fin de entre ambos cabos se
                        va ensangostando, y estas puntas en circunferencia de cincuenta mil pasos
                        dejan la Isla en forma de Luna nueva.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.2" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-02-01" n="em 1.2" corresp="#es-1-02-1">Estas extremidades
                        <pb n="1v"/>combatidas del mar se hallan distantes la una de la otra otros once mil y el
                        mar defendido de los vientos.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.3" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-03-1" n="em 1.3" corresp="#es-1-03-1">Entre estos brazos
                        forma un apacible lago, dejando un puerto acomodado desde donde, por su
                        oportunidad, envían sus flotas a otras provincias y países.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.4" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-04-1" n="em 1.4" corresp="#es-1-04-1">Las gargantas de las
                        entradas de la una parte con los bancos y bados y de la otra, con
                        disimulados escollos, ponen espanto al que pretende entrar como
                        enemigo.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.5" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-05-1" n="em 1.5" corresp="#es-1-05-1">Casi en el medio de
                        este espacio se ve otra roca no tan peligrosa, en cuya eminencia han
                        fabricado un fuerte, donde tienen presidio.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.6" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-06-1" n="em 1.6" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> Hállanse otros muchos
                        escollos ocultos, y por esto dañosos.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-06-2" n="em 1.7" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> Ellos solamente tienen
                        conocimiento de aquellos canales de donde procede que raras veces el
                        extranjero que no sea avisado de alguno de la Utopía pueda penetrallos, y
                        cuando con afán entre sin riesgo, no gobernándose por ciertas guías puestas
                        en la ribera, vendrá cualquier gran enemiga armada a dar al través.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.7" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-07-1" n="em 1.8" corresp="#es-1-7-1">De la otra parte, hay un
                        puerto bastantemente frecuentado y el desembarcadero fortificado por arte y
                        naturaleza, de manera que poca gente de guerra pondrán en retirada y
                        rebatirán el ímpetu de copioso ejército.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.8" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-08-1" n="em 1.9" corresp="#es-1-8-1">Hay opinión (y la
                        apariencia del lugar lo muestra) que aquella tierra en lo antiguo estaba
                        rodeada del mar.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.9" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-09-1" n="em 1.10" corresp="#es-1-9-1">Mas Utopo, de quien
                        tomó nombre la Isla por haberla conquistado (porque primero se llamaba
                        Abraxa), redujo aquella muche<pb n="2r"/>dumbre rústica y grosera a esta manera de vivir
                        humana y civil, cual sigue todo el linaje de los hombres.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.10" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-10-1" n="em 1.11" corresp="#es-1-10-1">Cortó un istmo de diez
                        mil pasos por el cual estaba Utopía continente con la tierra firme, con que
                        quedó hecha Isla.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.11" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-11-1" n="em 1.12" corresp="#es-1-11-1">Habiendo constreñido
                        no solo a los moradores antiguos, mas también a sus soldados, por no causar
                        afrenta a aquellos.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-11-2" n="em 1.13" corresp="#es-1-11-1"> Y con tanto número de
                        operarios en brevísimo tiempo acabó el trabajo, dejando admirados los
                        pueblos vecinos, que al principio del intento.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.12" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-12-1" n="em 1.14" corresp="#es-1-12-1">Hay en esta Isla
                        cincuenta y cuatro ciudades, conformes en lengua, institutos, y leyes, y
                        casi a un modelo fabricadas, en cuanto el sitio lo permite.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.13" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-13-1" n="em 1.15" corresp="#es-1-13-1">Las más cercanas están
                        desviadas veinticuatro mil pasos, mas ninguna se halla tan apartada una de
                        otra, que en un día no pueda hacer jornada a ellas un peón.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.14" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-14-1" n="em 1.16" corresp="#es-1-14-1">Tres ciudadanos
                        expertos y ancianos de cada una destas ciudades todos los años concurren en
                        Amauroto, la cual, por estar asentada en medio de la Isla, es a todos cómoda
                        y tenida por principal y cabeza, donde tratan de la causa común y pública de
                        toda la Utopía.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.15" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-15-1" n="em 1.17" corresp="#es-1-15-1">Las ciudades no tienen
                        de término pasados de veinte mil pasos en contorno, algunas más.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-15-2" n="em 1.18" corresp="#es-1-15-1">Conforme están
                        desviadas y apartadas más o menos entre sí, ninguna dellas desea extender, o
                        dilatar su distrito, juzgándose antes usufructuarios labradores de los
                        campos que señores dellos.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.16" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-16-1" n="em 1.19" corresp="#es-1-16-1">Tienen alquerías muy
                        prevenidas <pb n="2v"/>de todos los instrumentos para la labor y agricultura; y a estos
                        cortijos van a poblar los ciudadanos.</seg></seg>
                  <seg n="1.17" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-17-1" n="em 1.20" corresp="#es-1-17-1">Ninguna familia
                        rústica destas tiene menos de cuarenta personas, excepto dos hombres del
                        campo.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.18" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-18-1" n="em 1.21" corresp="#es-1-18-1">A todo este número se
                        le señala padre y madre de familias, por edad y costumbres venerables, y a
                        cada treinta cortijos se le propone cabeza.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.19" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-19-1" n="em 1.22" corresp="#es-1-19-1">Vuelven a la ciudad en
                        cada un año veinte de los de estas familias de los que han residido dos en
                        las alquerías.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.20" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-20-1" n="em 1.23" corresp="#es-1-20-1">Suceden a estos otros
                        tantos de la ciudad para que sean ejercitados en la agricultura, por los que
                        quedan expertos con la residencia de un año, y que el venidero enseñen a
                        otros, a intento que no falte en todos la experiencia de la labranza, que al
                        tiempo de recoger los frutos se hallen hábiles.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.21" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-21-1" n="em 1.24" corresp="#es-1-21-1">Y aunque esta manera
                        de renovar la agricultura se acostumbra, porque ninguno se halle obligado a
                        continuar la vida rústica más tiempo, no por esto muchos que se deleitasen
                        en la agricultura dejasen de estar allí más años.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.22" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-22-1" n="em 1.25" corresp="#es-1-22-1">Los labradores
                        cultivan el terreno, sustentan los animales, aperciben leña y la conducen a
                        la ciudad por tierra o por mar, como les viene más a propósito.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.23" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-23-1" n="em 1.26" corresp="#es-1-23-1">Sacan con admirable
                        artificio una infinidad de pollos, porque sin empollar las gallinas con un
                        calor proporcionado los dan vida y después los hombres los abrigan y
                        gobiernan.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.24" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-24-1" n="em 1.27" corresp="#es-1-24-1">Sustentan pocos
                        caballos y feroces, de los cuales se sirven solamente en las empresas de
                        <pb n="3r"/>guerra, porque las demás labores de cultivar y conducir las ejecutan con los
                        bueyes, los cuales bien que sean más lentos que los caballos todavía en el
                        ejercicio son más sufridos y menos sujetos a enfermedades fuera de que son
                        de menos gasto y, cuando no se puede por la vejez usar dellos, se pueden
                        comer.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.25" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-25-1" n="em 1.28" corresp="#es-1-25-1">Siembran solamente
                        trigo, beben vino de uvas y gastan sidra, o agua pura, o cocida con regaliz,
                        de que tienen mucha abundancia.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.26" type="singleSentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-26-1" n="em 1.29" corresp="#es-1-26-1">Y aunque tantean
                        cuanta vitualla se consuma en la ciudad y el contorno, sin embargo, siembran
                        más para dar a los vecinos.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.27" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-27-1" n="em 1.30" corresp="#es-1-27-1">Todo instrumento de la
                        labranza se toma de la ciudad por mano del magistrado sin costa alguna, y
                        muchos concurren todos los meses en los pueblos a las fiestas
                        solemnes.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="em-1-27-2" n="em 1.31" corresp="#es-1-27-1">Cuando es tiempo de
                        segar los panes, los que gobiernan la labranza avisan a los magistrados
                        cuanto número de ciudadanos deban enviar a la siega; y, concurriendo todos a
                        un tiempo en día sereno, casi ponen en cobro todo el grano.</seg>
                  </seg>
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="original" xml:lang="es">
            <head type="work">Sermonis quem Raphael Hythlodaeus de optimo reipublicae statu habuit,
               liber secundus, per Thomam Morum ciuem et uicecomitem londinensem.</head>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head type="chapter"/>
               <ab>
                  <seg n="1.1" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-01-1" n="la 1.1" corresp="#es-1-01-1"> Vtopiensium insula in
                        media sui parte (nam hac latissima est) millia passuum ducenta porrigitur,
                        magnumque per insulae spatium non multo angustior, fines uersus paulatim
                        utrinque tenuatur.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-01-2" n="la 1.2" corresp="#es-1-01-1">hi uelut circunducti
                        circino quingentorum ambitu millium, insulam totam in lunae speciem
                        renascentis effigiant.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.2" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-02-1" n="la 1.3" type="partial" part="I" next="#la-1-03-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-02-1">Cuius cornua fretum interfluens millibus passuum plus
                        minus undecim dirimit, ac per ingens inane diffusum, circumiectu undique
                        terrae prohibitis uentis, </seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.3" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-03-1" n="la 1.3" type="partial" part="F" prev="#la-1-02-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-03-1">uasti in morem lacus, stagnans magis quam saeuiens,
                        omnem prope eius terrae aluum pro portu facit, magnoque hominum usu naues
                        quaqua uersus transmittit.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.4" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-04-1" n="la 1.4" corresp="#es-1-04-1">fauces hinc uadis inde
                        saxis formidolosae.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.5" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-05-1" n="la 1.5" corresp="#es-1-05-1">In medio ferme
                        interstitio una rupes eminet, eoque innoxia, cui inaedificatam turrim
                        praesidio tenent: caeterae latentes et insidiosae.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.6" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-06-1" n="la 1.6" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> Canales solis ipsis
                        noti; atque ideo non temere accidit ut exterus quisquam hunc in sinum, nisi
                        Vtopiano duce, penetret; ut in quern uix ipsis tutus ingressus est, nisi
                        signis quibusdam e litore uiam regentibus.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-06-2" n="la 1.7" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> His in diuersa
                        translatis loca, hostium quamlibet numerosam classem facile in pemiciem
                        traherent.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.7" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-07-1" n="la 1.8" corresp="#es-1-7-1">Ab altera parte non
                        infrequentes portus.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-07-2" n="la 1.9" corresp="#es-1-7-1"> At ubique descensus in
                        terram ita natura munitus, aut arte, ut ingentes copiae paucis inde queant
                        propugnatoribus arceri.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.8" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-08-1" n="la 1.10" corresp="#es-1-8-1">Caeterum, uti fertur,
                        utique ipsa loci facies prae se fert, ea tellus olim non ambiebatur
                        mari.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.9" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-09-1" n="la 1.11" type="partial" part="I" next="#la-10-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-9-1">Sed Vtopus, cuius utpote uictoris nomen refert insula
                        (nam ante id tempus Abraxa dicebatur) quique rudem atque agrestem turbam ad
                        id, quo nunc caeteros prope mortales antecellit, cultus humanitatisque
                        perduxit, </seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.10" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-10-1" n="la 1.11" type="partial" part="F" next="#la-09-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-10-1">primo protinus appulsu uictoria potitus, passuum milia
                        quindecim, qua parte tellus continenti adhaesit, exscindendum curauit, ac
                        mare circum terram duxit.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.11" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-11-1" n="la 1.12" corresp="#es-1-11-1">Quumque ad id operis
                        non incolas modo coegisset (ne contumeliae loco laborem ducerent) sed suos
                        praeterea milites omnes adiungeret, in tantam hominuni multitudinem opere
                        distributo, incredibili celeritate res perfecta; finitimosque (qui initio
                        uanitatem incoepti riserant) admiratione successus ac terrore
                        perculerit.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.12" type="multisentence">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-12-1" n="la 1.13" corresp="#es-1-12-1">Insula ciuitates habet
                        quatuor et quinquaginta, spatiosas omnes ac magnificas, lingua, moribus,
                        institutis, legibus prorsus iisdem.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-12-2" n="la 1.14" corresp="#es-1-12-1">idem situs omnium,
                        eadem ubique quatenusper locum licet rerum facies.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.13" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-13-1" n="la 1.15" corresp="#es-1-13-1">Harum quae proximae
                        inter sunt, millia quatuor ac uiginti separant.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-13-2" n="la 1.16" corresp="#es-1-13-1">Nulla rursus est tam
                        deserta, e qua non ad aliam urbem pedibus queat unius itinere diei
                        perueniri.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.14" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-14-1" n="la 1.17" corresp="#es-1-14-1">Ciues quaque ex urbe
                        terni senes ac rerum periti tractatum de rebus insulae communibus quotannis
                        conueniunt Amaurotum.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-14-2" n="la 1.18" corresp="#es-1-14-1">Nam ea urbs (quod
                        tanquam in umbilico terrae sita maxime iacet omnium partium legatis
                        opportuna) prima princepsque habetur.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.15" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-15-1" n="la 1.19" corresp="#es-1-15-1">Agri ita commode
                        ciuitatibus assignati sunt, ut ab nulla parte minus soli quam XX passuum
                        millia una quaeuis habeat, ab aliqua multo etiam amplius; uidelicet qua
                        parte longius urbes inter se disiunguntur.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-15-2" n="la 1.20" corresp="#es-1-15-1">Nulli urbi cupido
                        promouendorum finium.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-15-3" n="la 1.21" corresp="#es-1-15-1">Quippe quos habent,
                        agricolas magis eorum se, quam dominos, putant.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.16" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-16-1" n="la 1.22" corresp="#es-1-16-1">Habent ruri per omnes
                        agros commode dispositas domos, rusticis instrumentis instructas.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-16-2" n="la 1.23" corresp="#es-1-16-1">Hae habitantur ciuibus
                        per uices eo commigrantibus.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.17" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-17-1" n="la 1.24" type="partial" part="I" next="#la-1-18-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-17-1">Nulla familia rustica in uiris mulieribusque pauciores
                        habet quam quadraginta, praeter duos asscriptitios seruos, .</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.18" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-18-1" n="la 1.24" type="partial" part="F" prev="#la-1-17-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-18-1">quibus pater materque familias graues ac maturi
                        praeficiuntur; et singulis tricenis familiis philarchus unus.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.19" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-19-1" n="la 1.25" corresp="#es-1-19-1">E quaque familia
                        uiginti quotannis in urbem remigrant, hi qui biennium ruri compleuere.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.20" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-20-1" n="la 1.26" corresp="#es-1-20-1">In horum locum totidem
                        recentes ex urbe subrogantur, ut ab his qui annum ibi fuere, atque ideo
                        rusticarum peritiores rerum, instituantur ; alios anno sequente docturi: ne,
                        si pariter omnes ibi noui agricolationisque rudes essent, aliquid in annona
                        per imperitiam peccaretur.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.21" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-21-1" n="la 1.27" corresp="#es-1-21-1">Is innouandorum
                        agricolarum mos etsi solemnis sit, n quisquam inuitus asperiorem uitam
                        cogatur continuare diutius ; multi tamen, quos rusticae rei studium natura
                        delectat, plures sibi annos impetrant.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.22" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-22-1" n="la 1.28" corresp="#es-1-22-1"> Agricolae terram
                        colunt, nutriunt animalia, ligna comparant, atque in urbem qua commodum est
                        terra mariue conuehunt.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.23" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-23-1" n="la 1.29" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> Pullorum infinitam
                        educant multitudinem, mirabili artificio.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-23-2" n="la 1.30" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> Neque enim incubant
                        oua gallinae; sed magnum eorum numerum calore quodam aequabili fouentes
                        animant educantque.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-23-3" n="la 1.31" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> Hi simul atque e
                        testa prodiere, homines uice matrum comitantur et agnoscunt.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.24" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-24-1" n="la 1.32" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> Equos alunt perquam
                        paucos, nee nisi ferocientes, neque alium in usum quam exercendae rebus
                        equestribus iuuentuti.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-24-2" n="la 1.33" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> Nam omnem seu colendi
                        sed uehendi laborem boues obeunt; quos, ut fatentur equis impetu cedere, sic
                        patientia uincere, nec tot obnoxios morbis putant; ad haec minore impendio
                        et operae et sumptus ali, ac denique laboribus emeritos in cibum tandem usui
                        esse.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.25" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-25-1" n="la 1.34" corresp="#es-1-25-1"> Semente in solum
                        panem utuntur.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-25-2" n="la 1.35" corresp="#es-1-25-1"> Nam aut uuarum uinum
                        bibunt, aut pomorum pirorumue, aut denique aquam nonnunquam meram; saepe
                        etiam qua mel aut glycyrizam incoxerint, cuius baud exiguam habent
                        copiam.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.26" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-26-1" n="la 1.36" corresp="#es-1-26-1">Quum exploratum
                        habeant (habent enim certissimum) quantum annonae consumat urbs, et
                        circumiectus urbi conuentus, tamen multo amplius et sementis faciunt et
                        pecudum educant, quam quod in -suos usus sufficiat, reliquum impartituri
                        finitimis.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.27" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-27-1" n="la 1.37" corresp="#es-1-27-1"> Quibuscunque rebus
                        opus est, quae res ruri non habentur, eam supellectilem omnem ab urbe
                        petunt, et sine ulla rerum cemmutatione a magistratibus urbanis nullo
                        negocio consequuntur.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-27-2" n="la 1.38" corresp="#es-1-27-1">Nam illo singulo
                        quoque mense plerique ad festum diem conueniunt.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="la-1-27-3" n="la 1.39" corresp="#es-1-27-1">Quum frumentandi dies
                        instat, magistratibus urbanis agricolarum phylarchi denunciant, quantum
                        ciuium numerum ad se mitti conueniat; quae multitudo frumentatorum, quum ad
                        ipsum diem opportune adsit, uno prope sereno die tota frumentatione
                        defungutur.</seg>
                  </seg>
               </ab>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
            <head type="work">The second Boke of the communication of Raphael Hythlodaye,
               concernyng the best state of a common wealthe: conteynyng the discription of Vtopia,
               with a large declaration of the Godly gouernement, and of all the good lawes and
               orders of the same Ilande.</head>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head type="chapter"/>
               <ab>
                  <seg n="1.1" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-01-1" n="en 1.1" corresp="#es-1-01-1"> The Ilande of Vtopia
                        conteyneth in breadthe in the myddell part of it (for there it is brodest)
                        CC miles.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-01-2" n="en 1.2" corresp="#es-1-01-1"> Whiche bredthe
                        continueth through the moste parte of the lande, sauyng that by lytle and
                        lytle it commeth in and waxeth narrower towardes both the endes.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-01-3" n="en 1.3" corresp="#es-1-01-1"> Whiche fetchynge about
                        a circuite or compasse of vc myles, do fassion the hole Ilande lyke to the
                        newe mone.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.2" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-02-1" n="en 1.4" type="partial" part="I" next="#en-1-03-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-02-1">Betwene thys two corners the sea runneth in, diuydyng
                        them a sonder by the distaunce of xi miles or there aboutes, and there
                        surmounteth into a large and wyde sea, which, by reason that the lande of
                        euery syde compasseth it about, and shiltreth it from the windes,</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.3" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-03-1" n="en 1.4" type="partial" part="F" prev="#en-1-02-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-03-1"> is not rough nor mountith not with great waues, but
                        almost floweth quietlye, not muche vnlike a great standing powle; and maketh
                        almoste al the space within the bellye of the lande in maner of a hauen; and
                        to the great commoditie of the lnhabitauntes receaueth in shyppes towardes
                        euery parte of the lande.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.4" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-04-1" n="en 1.5" corresp="#es-1-04-1">The forefrontes or
                        frontiers of the ii corners, what wythe fordys and shelues, and what with
                        rockes, be very ieoperdous and daungerous.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.5" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-05-1" n="en 1.6" corresp="#es-1-05-1">In the middel distaunce
                        between them both standeth vp aboue the water a great rocke, which therfore
                        is nothing perillous bicause it is in sight.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-05-2" n="en 1.7" corresp="#es-1-05-1"> Vpon the top of this
                        rocke is a faire and a strong towre builded, which thei holde with a garison
                        of men.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.6" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-06-1" n="en 1.8" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> Other rockes ther be,
                        that lye hidde vnder the water, and therefore be daungerous.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-06-2" n="en 1.9" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> The channelles be
                        knowen onely to themselfes.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-06-3" n="en 1.10" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> An therfore it
                        seldome chaunceth that any straunger, oneles he be guided by a Vtopian, can
                        come in to this hauen.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-06-4" n="en 1.11" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> In so muche that they
                        themselfes could skaselie entre without ieoperdie, but that their way is
                        directed and ruled by certaine lande markes standing on the shore.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-06-5" n="en 1.12" corresp="#es-1-06-1"> By turning,
                        translatynge, and remouinge this markes into other places, they maye
                        destroye their enemies nauies, be thei neuer so many.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.7" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-07-1" n="en 1.13" corresp="#es-1-7-1">The out side of the
                        lande is also full of hauens; but the landing is so surely defenced, what by
                        nature and what by workmanshyp of mans hande, that a fewe defenders maye
                        dryue backe many armies.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.8" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-08-1" n="en 1.14" corresp="#es-1-8-1">Howbeit, as they saye,
                        and as the fassion of the place it selfe doth partely shewe, it was not euer
                        compassed about with the sea.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.9" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-09-1" n="en 1.15" type="partial" part="I" next="#en-1-10-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-9-1">But kyng Vtopus, whose name as conquerour the Iland
                        beereth (for before that tyme it was called Abraxa), which also brought the
                        rude and wild people to that excellent perfection, in al good fassions,
                        humanitie, and ciuile gentilnes, wherin they now go beyond al the people of
                        the world; .</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.10" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-10-1" n="en 1.15" type="partial" part="F" prev="#en-1-09-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-10-1">euen at his first arriuinge and enteringe vpon the
                        lande, furth with obteynynge the victory caused xv myles space of vplandyshe
                        grounde, where the sea had no passage, to be cut and dygged vp; and so
                        brought the sea rounde aboute the lande.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.11" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-11-1" n="en 1.16" corresp="#es-1-11-1"> He set to thys worke
                        not only the inhabitauntes of the Ilande (because they should not thynke it
                        done in contumelye and despyte), but also all hys owne soldiours.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-11-2" n="en 1.17" corresp="#es-1-11-1"> Thus the worke, beyng
                        diuyded into so great a numbre of workemen, was with exceding maruelous
                        spede dyspatched.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-11-3" n="en 1.18" corresp="#es-1-11-1"> In so muche that the
                        borderers, whiche at the fyrst began to mocke and to gieste at thys vayne
                        enterpryse, then turned theyr laughter to marueyle at the successe, and to
                        feare.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.12" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-12-1" n="en 1.19" corresp="#es-1-12-1"> There be in the
                        Ilande liiii large and faire cities or shiere townes, agreyng all together
                        in one tonge, in lyke maners, institucions, and lawes.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-12-2" n="en 1.20" corresp="#es-1-12-1"> They be all set and
                        situate a lyke, and in all poyntes fashioned a lyke, as farfurth as the
                        place or plotte suffereth.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.13" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-13-1" n="en 1.21" corresp="#es-1-13-1"> Of thies cyties they
                        that be nighest together be xxiiii myles a sonder.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-13-2" n="en 1.22" corresp="#es-1-13-1"> Again there is none
                        of them distaunt from the next aboue one dayes iorneye a fote.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.14" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-14-1" n="en 1.23" corresp="#es-1-14-1"> There cum yearly to
                        Amaurote out of euery cytie iii olde men, wyse and well experienced, there
                        to entreate and debate of the common matters of the lande.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-14-2" n="en 1.24" corresp="#es-1-14-1"> For thys cytie
                        (because it standeth iust in the myddes of the Ilande, and is therfore moste
                        mete for the embassadours of all partes of the realme) is taken for the
                        chiefe and head cytie.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.15" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-15-1" n="en 1.25" corresp="#es-1-15-1"> The precinctes and
                        boundes of the shieres be so commodiously appoynted out, and set furth for
                        the cyties, that neuer a one of them all hath of anye syde lesse then xx
                        myles of grounde, and of som syde also muche more, as of that part where the
                        cyties be of farther distaunce a sonder.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-15-2" n="en 1.26" corresp="#es-1-15-1"> None of the cities
                        desire to enlarge the boundes and lymites of their shieres.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-15-3" n="en 1.27" corresp="#es-1-15-1"> For they count them
                        selfes rather the good husbandes, then the owners of their landes.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.16" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-16-1" n="en 1.28" corresp="#es-1-16-1"> They haue in the
                        countrey in all partes of the shiere howses or fermes buylded, wel appointed
                        and furnyshed with all sortes of instrumentes and tooles belongyng to
                        husbandrie.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-16-2" n="en 1.29" corresp="#es-1-16-1"> Thies houses be
                        inhabited of the cytezens, whiche cum thyther to dwel by course.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.17" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-17-1" n="en 1.30" type="partial" part="I" next="#en-1-18-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-17-1">No howsholde or ferme in the countrey hath fewer then
                        xl persones, men and women, besydes two bonden men, .</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.18" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-18-1" n="en 1.30" type="partial" part="F" prev="#en-1-17-1"
                        corresp="#es-1-18-1"> whiche be all vnder the rule and order of the good man
                        and the good wyfe of the house, beynge bothe very sage and discrete
                        persones.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-18-2" n="en 1.31" corresp="#es-1-18-1"> And euery xxx fermes
                        or famelies haue one heade ruler, whiche is called a Phylarche, being as it
                        were a hed baylyffe.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.19" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-19-1" n="en 1.32" corresp="#es-1-19-1">Out of euery one of
                        thies famelies or fermes cummeth euery yeare into the cytie xx persones
                        whiche haue contynewed ii yeres before in the countrey.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.20" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-20-1" n="en 1.33" corresp="#es-1-20-1"> In their place so
                        manye freshe be sent thither out of the citie, whiche of them that haue bene
                        there a yeare all ready, and be therfore expert and conninge in husbandry,
                        shalbe instructed and taught; and they the next yeare shall teache
                        other.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-20-2" n="en 1.34" corresp="#es-1-20-1"> This order is vsed,
                        for feare that other skarsenes of victualles or some other like incommoditie
                        shuld chaunce through lacke of knowledge, yf they should be al together newe
                        and fresh and vnexperte in husbandrie.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.21" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-21-1" n="en 1.35" corresp="#es-1-21-1">This maner and fassion
                        of yearlye chaunginge and renewinge the occupiers of husbandrie, though it
                        be solempne and customablie vsed, to thintent that no man shall be
                        constrayned against his wil to contynewe longe in that harde and sharpe
                        kynde of lyfe, yet manye of them haue suche a pleasure and delete in
                        husbandrye, that they obteyne a longer space of yeares.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.22" type="singleSentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-22-1" n="en 1.36" corresp="#es-1-22-1">Thies husbandmen plowe
                        and till the grounde, and bryde vp cattell, and make readye woode, whiche
                        they carrye to the cytie, other by lande or by water, as they maye moste
                        conuenyently.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.23" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-23-1" n="en 1.37" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> They brynge vp a
                        greate multytude of pulleyne, and that by a meruelous policie.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-23-2" n="en 1.38" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> For the hennes doo
                        not syt vpon the egges: but by kepynge them in a certayne equall heate, they
                        brynge lyfe into them, and hatche them.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-23-3" n="en 1.39" corresp="#es-1-23-1"> The chykens, assone
                        as they be come owte of the shell, followe men and women in steade of the
                        hennes.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.24" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-24-1" n="en 1.40" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> They bryng vp very
                        fewe horses; nor non, but very fearce ones; and for none other vse or
                        purpose, but only to exercyse their youthe in rydynge and feates of
                        armes.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-24-2" n="en 1.41" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> For oxen be put to
                        all the labour of plowynge and drawyng.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-24-3" n="en 1.42" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> Whiche they graunte
                        to be not so good as horses as sodeyne brunt, and (as we saye) at a dead
                        lifte;  but yet they holde opinion, that oxen wyll abyde and suffre much
                        more laboure and payne then horses wyl.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-24-4" n="en 1.43" corresp="#es-1-24-1"> And they thinke that
                        they be not in daunger and subiecte vnto so manye dysseases, and that they
                        bee kepte and maynteyned wyth muche lesse coste and charge; and fynally that
                        they be good for meate when they be past labour.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.25" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-25-1" n="en 1.44" corresp="#es-1-25-1"> They sowe corne onlye
                        for bread.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-25-2" n="en 1.45" corresp="#es-1-25-1"> For their drynke is
                        other wyne made of grapes, or els of apples or peares, or els it is cleane
                        water; and many tymes methe made of honey or liqueresse sodde in water, for
                        therof they haue great store.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.26" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-26-1" n="en 1.46" corresp="#es-1-26-1"> And though they knowe
                        certeynlye (for they knowe it perfetly in dede), how much victayles the
                        cytie with the hole countrey or shiere rounde a boute it dothe spende; yet
                        they sowe much more corne, and bryed vp muche more cattell, then serueth for
                        their own vse.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-26-2" n="en 1.47" corresp="#es-1-26-1"> And the ouerplus they
                        parte amonge their borderers.</seg>
                  </seg>
                  <seg n="1.27" type="multisentence" subtype="translated">
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-27-1" n="en 1.48" corresp="#es-1-27-1"> What soeuer necessary
                        thynges be lackynge in the countrey, all suche stuffe they fetche out of the
                        citie; where without anye exchaunge they easelye obteyne it of the
                        magistrates of the citie.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-27-2" n="en 1.49" corresp="#es-1-27-1"> For euerye moneth
                        manye of them goo into the cytie on the hollye daye.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-27-3" n="en 1.50" corresp="#es-1-27-1"> When theyr haruest
                        daye draweth nere and is at hande, then the Philarches, whiche be the hed
                        officers and bayliffes of husbandrye, sende woorde to the magistrates of the
                        citie, what numbre of haruest men is nedefull to bee sente to them out of
                        the cytie.</seg>
                     <seg xml:id="en-1-27-4" n="en 1.51" corresp="#es-1-27-1"> The whiche companye
                        of haruest men, beyng there readye at the daye appoynted, almoste in one
                        fayre daye dispatcheth all the haruest woorke.</seg>
                  </seg>
               </ab>
            </div>        
         </div>
         <div type="notes">
            <note n="1" xml:id="n-1-1" target="#note-1-1">Medinilla translates <hi>quingentorum</hi> into Spanish as
               <hi>cincuenta</hi> [fifty] instead of <hi>quinientos</hi> [five hundreds]. López Estrada
               already mentioned Medinilla's mistranslations of numbers (1965, 308).</note>
            <note n="2" xml:id="n-1-2" target="#note-1-2">Medinilla translates the Latin word
               <hi>praesidium</hi> as <hi>presidio</hi> [garrison]. According to Covarrubias, this is the
               place where soldiers keep guard (1611, 595v). In today's Spanish this word refers to a
               penitentiary institution (RAE 2023).</note>
            <note n="3" xml:id="n-1-3" target="#note-1-3">Medinilla seems to miss the agreement
               between the Latin adjective <hi>infrequentes</hi> and the fourth-declension noun <hi>portus</hi>.
               That is why he translates the Latin "ab altera parte non infrequentes portus" (More 1965, 110, line 27) as "on the other side, there is a frequently visited
               harbor" instead of something like "on the outer side of the island, harbors are many" (More 1965, 111, line 31). Also, Thomas
               More indicates that some harbors are fortified by nature, <hi>natura</hi> in Latin, and other by works, <hi>arte</hi>,
               and Medinilla, on the contrary, renders it as if ports are fortified by both ("por arte i
               naturaleza" [in English, "by art and nature"]).</note>
            <note n="4" xml:id="n-1-4" target="#note-1-4">This is one of the examples where
               Medinilla uses the verb <hi>haber</hi> instead of <hi>tener</hi>. Besides, the translator makes an
               incorrect translation of "ea tellus olim non ambiebatur mari" (More 1965, 112, line 1). Medinilla opts for
               "aquella tierra en lo antiguo estaba rodeada del mar" ["that land was surrounded by the sea in ancient
               times"] instead of "the island once was not surrounded by sea" (More 1965, 113, line 2).</note>
            <note n="5" xml:id="n-1-5" target="#note-1-5">He translates <hi>perduxit</hi> into <hi>redujo</hi>.
               The Latin verb <hi>perduco</hi> means "conduct, guide", whereas the Spanish <hi>reducir</hi>
               implies some control or power, forcing someone into doing something. Darcy Kern agrees on this, as she comments on the
               Tacitist influence of this decision (2024, 226).</note>
            <note n="6" xml:id="n-1-6" target="#note-1-6">Medinilla does not translate "primo
               protinus appulsu uictoria potitus" (More 1965, 112, line 5) ["gained a victory at his very first landing" (More 1965, 113, lines 7-8)]. It is likely that he found this information
               redundant with what has previously been said.</note>
            <note n="7" xml:id="n-1-7" target="#note-1-7">Medinilla translates "ne contumeliae loco
               laboren ducerent" (More 1965, 112, line 10) very freely and in a different sense: "por no causar afrenta a
               aquellos" ["so as not to make them feel dishonoured"]. The English
               translation in Yale reads "to prevent them from thinking the labor a disgrace" (More 1965,
               113, line 15). Also, the translator misses the fear overtone at the end, presented in
               Latin as <hi>terrore</hi>.</note>
            <note n="8" xml:id="n-1-8" target="#note-1-8">Medinilla omits "spatiosas omnes ac
               magnificas" (More 1965, 112, line 16) ["all spacious and magnificent" (More 1965, 113, lines 19-20)]. Also, he removes <hi>moribus</hi> [traditions] from the list of elements.</note>
            <note n="9" xml:id="n-1-9" target="#note-1-9">Medinilla introduces the word <hi>peón</hi> to
               refer to the person who walks certain distance on foot, which coincides with the definition of this term in the <hi>Tesoro de la Lengua</hi>,
               defining it as "el que camina a pie, el que en las obras mercenarias trabaja por su
               jornal... " ["the person who walks or goes on foot, the person engaged who works
               to receive a daily wage"] (Covarrubias 1611, 584r).</note>
            <note n="10" xml:id="n-1-10" target="#note-1-10">Medinilla does not translate <hi>legatis</hi>,
               which appears as "embassadours" in Robinson's translation (More 1895, 120) and "representatives" in the Yale
               edition (More 1965, 112, line 25).</note>
            <note n="11" xml:id="n-1-11" target="#note-1-11">Medinilla translates <hi>XX passuum
               millia</hi> [twenty miles] as <hi>veinte</hi> [twenty]. This implies he used a 1518 edition of Utopia, since in
               the 1516 and 1517 editions the number is <hi>duodecim</hi> [twelve].</note>
            <note n="12" xml:id="n-1-12" target="#note-1-12">The Spanish translator choses the pair <hi>alquería y cortijos</hi> to render
               <hi>domos</hi>. <hi>Alqueria</hi> appears in the <hi>Tesoro de la lengua</hi> with the meaning of "es la casa sola en el campo donde el labrador del,
               se recoge con su gente y hato de labrança, por estar lejos de poblado, 
               y que el dia se le fuera en ir y venir, no habitando en la misma tierra que labra, y asi vale tanto como casa de labranza,
               y donde hay muchas destas casas, apartadas unas de otras"
               ["it is the single house in the field where the farmer gathers with his people and farm equipment,
               because it is far from town, and the day would be spent coming and going,
               not living on the same land where he farms, and so it is worth as much as a farmhouse,
               and where there are many of these houses, separated from each other"] (Covarrubias 1611, 81v). Besides, according to
               the <hi>Diccionario de Autoridades</hi>, <hi>cortijo</hi> means the same but was commonly used in areas of Castille and
               Andalusia (RAE 1729). Medinilla, possibly following Jiménez Patón's theory, uses local words, which set the
               translation into a local context. López Estrada already discussed the introduction of dialectal expressions in this translation (1965, 306).</note>
            <note n="13" xml:id="n-1-13" target="#note-1-13">The 1637 translation preserves the
               expression <hi>familia rústica</hi> for the Latin <hi>familia rustica</hi>. Robinson opts for
               "howsholde or ferme in the countrey". Medinilla translates <hi>praeter</hi> as <hi>excepto</hi>
               [except]. This removes the sense of addition <hi>praeter</hi> originally conveys.</note>
            <note n="14" xml:id="n-1-14" target="#note-1-14">Whereas Medinilla finds the Spanish
               word <hi>cabeza</hi> [head] for the Latin <hi>philarchus</hi>, Robinson transfers the Latin word
               (originally in Greek <hi>φύλαρχος</hi>) into English with his choice "Phylarche". This is the first
               time, according to the OED, this word is used in this language. Hexter and Surtz
               comment on the ironic connection between the Greek terms <hi>φύλαρχος</hi> and <hi>φ́ιλαρχος</hi>, the
               first meaning "the head of a tribe" and the second, "fond of rule and power" (More 1965, 389, note 114/7).
               The introduction of this neologism in Robinson's requests an explicative
               sentence later ("being as it were a hed baylyffe"), which does not appear in the
               original Latin.</note>
            <note n="15" xml:id="n-1-15" target="#note-1-15">There is an ellipsis of the word <hi>año</hi>
               [year] at the end the sentence.</note>
            <note n="16" xml:id="n-1-16" target="#note-1-16">The translator does not keep the
               humorous idea that chickens follow men as if they were hens as in "homines uice matrum
               comitantur et agnoscunt" (More 1965, 114, line 23) ["the chick follows and acknowledge humans as their mothers" (More 1965, 115, lines 30-31)].</note>
            <note n="17" xml:id="n-1-17" target="#note-1-17">Medinilla seems to summarize the
               content, omitting ideas like "tamen multo amplius et sementis faciunt et peducum
               educant" (More 1965, 116, lines 8-9) ["they produce far more grain and cattle than they require for their own
               use" (More 1965, 117, lines 10-11)].</note>
            <note n="18" xml:id="n-1-18" target="#note-1-18">Medinilla opts to render <hi>urbs</hi> once as
               <hi>ciudad</hi> [city] and another as <hi>pueblo</hi> [town] in this segment. It seems he establishes a
               difference between the city, which is the main town, and the rest of them. This could
               lead to confusion, as <hi>pueblos</hi> are today deemed as cities with smaller number of
               inhabitants and services available and, as seen in later examples, the translator
               generally uses <hi>pueblo</hi> to translate the Latin word <hi>populus</hi>. There is another
               relevant example in Chapter VI. This displays a sense of locality and adjustment to
               the reality in Spain.</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
